The Tale Of Despereaux
浪漫的老鼠
Once upon a time,
很久很久以前
there was a brave little mouse
有一只勇敢的小老鼠
who loved honor and justice and always told the truth.
他自尊自爱 明辨是非 总是据实直言
No, that's not him.
不 这个不是他
That's a rat.
这是只耗子
And anyone who knows anything,
任何有常识的人都知道
knows there's a big difference between a mouse and a rat.
老鼠和耗子是有很大区别的
First of all, rats hate the light.
首先 耗子讨厌阳光
They spend their lives in the darkness.
他们一辈子活在黑暗里
They're also terrified of people,
而且他们害怕人类
which is why they slink and cower all the time.
所以他们总是偷偷摸摸 东躲西藏
And as far as telling the truth is concerned,
而关于"据实直言"
well, that's impossible because, as everyone knows,
这是不可能的 因为谁都知道
a rat can't talk.
耗子不会说话
Tell me that thing again, please.
再跟我说一次 求你了
Come on.
拜托
Just once, I promise.
最后一次 我保证
Tell me one more time,
再对我说一次
and I won't ask you ever again. I swear.
我就不会再问你了 我发誓
Fine. We are headed to Dor,
好吧 我们要去多尔国
one of the most magical places in the whole world.
世界上最神奇的地方之一
No, that's not what you said before.
不 你之前不是这样说的
You know, every place has something special.
每个地方都有独一无二的东西
And, in Dor, it's the soup!
在多尔 最特别的是汤!
Land ho!
陆地!
It's down below, I tell you.
就在下面 我告诉过你
Give it a heave.
使劲拉
I can see it!
我看见它了!
Ooh, I can smell it! I can smell it.
哦 我能闻到它! 我能闻到它
Oh, I can't wait to taste the soup!
喔 我等不及想尝尝这儿的汤!
Just stay close.
别乱跑
We leave again at 6:00.
我们六点要离开
You know, we ought to think about staying here just a little longer.
知道么 我们该考虑在这儿多待一会儿
Don't even think about it.
想都别想
Remember Shanghai?
还记得上海吗?
Yeah, but this place is different.
记得 但这里不同
I mean, this is special.
我是说 这儿很特别
On any given day, just one whiff from one of the soup shops
在这里的每一天 闻一下汤店里飘出的香气
was almost like having a full meal.
就犹如让你饱餐一顿
But on one very special day every year,
但在每年一个特殊的日子里
the kingdom of Dor was magically transformed.
多尔举国上下热闹非凡
In Dor, Christmas was nothing.
在多尔 圣诞节不值一提
Well, they still celebrated it,
虽然他们仍然庆祝圣诞节
but it was nothing compared to Soup Day.
但和汤节相比 那就是小巫见大巫
Watch it, watch it.
小心 小心
Incoming potatoes!
土豆来啦!
Hurry! Hurry! Excuse us.
快啊! 快啊! 请让让
Every Dorian, young and old, would flock toward the castle
每个多尔人 无论老幼 都会聚集在城堡周围
because they knew that, at that very moment,
因为他们知道 此时此刻
deep within the royal kitchens,
皇室厨房的深处
a masterpiece was being created.
一件杰作即将诞生
Potatoes coming up!
土豆来啦!
Let's go!
开工啦!
Don't forget the parsley!
别忘记欧芹!
Make sure it's clean!
把欧芹洗干净!
Everyone knew Chef Andre was a genius,
全国上下都知道厨师Andre是个天才
but they got reminded of it on the first Sunday of every spring.
但在每年春天的第一个星期日 大家还是会被再次提醒
At exactly 12:00 noon,
中午十二点整
he would unveil that year's royal creation.
他会献上当年皇室厨房的新作
More onions!
加洋葱!
They would jam the town square,
百姓们聚集在广场上翘首以盼
and, as the aroma began to build,
随着香气越来越浓
so did their anticipation.
他们的期待也越来越高
Sorry.
对不起
Thank you.
谢谢
It's my pleasure to announce this year's royal creations
我很荣幸为大家宣布 今年皇室厨房的新作品
from the kitchens of Chef Andre.
Andre厨房最新研制的汤
Oh, no, no, no, no, no!
不 不 不 不 不 不!
Something is wrong.
哪里不对劲
I need more time!
我需要时间!
But we're late already!
可我们已经晚点了!
This is not right!
这汤不对劲!
Everyone out!
所有人都出去!
Out!
出去!
Now, it's hard to be a genius all by yourself.
要当一个天才 孤军奋战是很难的
In fact, sometimes, it takes a little help.
事实上 有时 天才也需要帮手
You changed something.
汤被你动了手脚
You're crazy. I did not touch it.
你疯了 我什么都没碰
- I can smell it. - Hmm?
- 我闻得出来 - 嗯?
- What's this? - What?
- 这是什么? - 什么?
- This! - Ow! Garlic.
- 这个! - 嗷! 是大蒜
- Garlic. - Yeah, a little garlic.
- 大蒜 - 是的 一颗小蒜头
- It was already there. - No.
- 本来就要加蒜的 - 不是
- Yes. - No.
- 是的 - 不是
- Yes. - Not this much!
- 是的 - 不是加那么多!
You ruined my soup!
你毁了我的汤!
I save your soup!
我救了你的汤!
Those people wait all year, and you want to give them this dishwater.
全国上下盼了一整年 你难道就给他们喝洗碗水
Dishwater?
洗碗水
Dishwater.
Dishwater?
洗碗水?
Ow! Cut it out!
嗷! 住手!
And this year's soup is
今年的汤是...
a spring tureen
一碗甘泉
配上各种烘烤过的蔬菜... with a mlange of roasted vegetables...
...fresh herbs... - Mmm!
新鲜的香草...
...and wild mushrooms.
还有野生蘑菇
Roscuro?
Oh. Evening.
哦 你好啊
I don't have to stand here and listen to a big talking garbage can!
我没必要站在这儿 听一个垃圾桶说话!
Ha! And I don't have to stand here and listen to a coward!
哈! 我更没必要站在这儿 听一个胆小鬼说话!
- Coward? - Yes, a coward!
- 胆小鬼? - 是的 胆小鬼!
- You call me coward? - Yes!
- 你说我胆小? - 没错!
Oh, no!
喔 不!
Oh, no, no, no, no, no.
喔 不 不 不 不 不
That did it.
这回完蛋了
- Hmm? - Mmm.
- 嗯? - 嗯
- Bellissima! - It's fantastique!
- 极品! - 太棒了!
Roscuro! Roscuro, where are you?
Roscuro! Roscuro 你在哪儿?
Voil?
请用
This is amazing!
令人叹为观止!
Wait till Your Highness tastes it.
请殿下您品尝
Hmm?
呃?
This is...
这汤真是...
...absolutely...
简直是...
Oh, it moved! My soup moved!
哦 它动了! 我的汤动了!
No, it isn't... It did not move.
不 它没有... 它没动
Oh, Your Highness.
哦 殿下
- Ahhh! - Darling?
- 啊! - 亲爱的?
Oh! A rat! There's a rat in my soup!
哦! 耗子! 我汤里有一只耗子!
Madam, I know that this is unfortunate.
夫人 我知道这令人不快
And I know that while on first glance, I might...
我知道 乍看之下 我可能...
- A rat! In my soup! - No. Please. Shh, shh, shh.
- 一只耗子! 在我的汤里! - 不 求你 嘘 嘘 嘘
- And I ate it! - Your Highness, hold on...
- 我喝了! - 陛下 等等...
- Uh-oh. - She's right! It's a rat!
- 啊哦 - 她没说错! 是只耗子!
- Please... - Ahhh! It's a rat!
- 拜托... - 啊! 是只耗子!
Get me that rat!
给我 抓住 那只 耗子!
Now, I really believe you're jumping to conclusions.
我真觉得您的决定太草率了
And I'm sure that the rats you met last time
我肯定 你遇见的上一只耗子
might have caused you to create a stereotype,
对你造成了很大困扰 使你对我有偏见
but... But I... But...
但是... 但是 我... 但是...
It's just... I'm just... I'm not really from around here.
只是... 我只是...我不是这个国家的
I'm... I'm from... Oh...
我... 我来自... 哦...
That's very aggressive.
太暴力了
Get him!
抓住他!
Kitchen...
厨房...
He's going into the kitchen!
他跑到厨房去了!
Over there!
在那儿!
Stop that rat!
抓住那只耗子!
I got him!
我抓住它了!
He's going near the soup!
它朝汤附近去了!
There he is!
他在这儿!
lf... If I could just tell...
能不能...能不能让我说两句...
On the kettle! That's him, right there!
在茶壶上! 它在那儿 就在那儿!
Look, up there!
瞧 在上面!
Sweetie? Darling?
亲爱的? 甜心?
She's... She's...
她... 她...
She's...
她...
Blimey, she's dead. Get him!
老天啊 她死了 抓住它!
Don't let him escape!
别让他逃了!
We'll get you, you rowdy rat!
我们要抓住你这只可恶的耗子!
No, no, no!
不 不 不!
No, not there!
不 不能掉在那里!
You don't need to be afraid.
你不必害怕
I know it's dark, but you'll get used to it.
我知道这儿很黑 但你会习惯的
Who... Who are you?
你... 你是谁?
Just a rat, like you.
我只是耗子 和你一样
Come with me.
跟我来
When something hurts this much, there must be a reason.
伤痛如此深重 肯定有其缘由
There must be someone to blame.
肯定有罪魁祸首
"From this moment on, soup,
从此刻起 汤...
"the making of soup, the selling of soup, or the eating of soup,
制作汤 卖汤 或者喝汤...
"is hereby outlawed in the kingdom of Dor!
在多尔国境内将被法律禁止!
"Rats are to be considered illegal as well
耗子也将不容于法律
"and are hereby deemed unlawful creatures in the kingdom of Dor!
在此宣布耗子是多尔国的非法动物!
"From this moment on,
从此刻起
"anyone harboring, sheltering or possessing a rat in any way,
以任何方式藏匿 收容或圈养耗子的人
"shall face the full wrath of the law!"
都将受到法律的严惩!
So think about this.
设想一下
What happens when you make something illegal that is just a natural part of the world?
将大自然的一部分定为非法 会有什么结果呢?
You may as well make flies illegal.
你也可以说苍蝇是非法的
Or sweat. Or Monday morning.
或者汗 或者星期一早晨
But that's what the King did out of a terrible sadness.
但国王偏偏就这样做了 因为沉重的悲伤
Sunlight left and the world went gray.
红日西斜 夜幕降临
Colors faded into each other and dark clouds filled the sky.
世界渐渐褪色 乌云遮蔽天空
And for a long time, it wouldn't rain.
很长一段时间 滴雨未落
The clouds just stayed and stayed and stayed.
乌云盘踞在头顶 久久不能散去
I wish it would rain.
真希望能下一场雨
You and the whole world, madam.
你和大家一样 殿下
Oh, sorry, milady!
哦 对不起 殿下!
Well, at least I can still feel that.
没关系 至少我还能感觉到疼痛
Louise, do you think there's a bit of light
Louise 你觉得世上的某处...
somewhere in the world?
是否还有一丝光明?
Don't know, ma'am.
我不知道 殿下
I think there is.
我想一定有
You just need to know where to find it.
只是你得知道 去哪儿找这丝光明
Okay, remember when we told you how,
好了 还记得刚才我说的...
once upon a time, there was this brave little mouse?
很久很久以前 有一只勇敢的小老鼠?
Well, if you know anything about fairytales,
如果你了解童话故事
you know that a hero doesn't appear
你就该知道 英雄不轻易出现
until the world really needs one.
除非世界没他不行
Oh, look out!
喔 小心!
Alms for the blind! Alms for the blind!
谁来施舍我这个可怜的瞎子!
老鼠的世界
Excuse me. Excuse me.
对不起 对不起
Excuse me.
对不起
- Whoa! - I'm sorry. Sorry.
- 哇喔! - 对不起 对不起
- Tilling? - Oh!
- Tilling? - 哦!
Mr. Mayor, hello!
镇长先生 你好啊!
Where are you going?
你这是要去哪儿?
Oh, well, my baby is having a...
哦 是这样的 我的孩子要生...
No, my wife is having a...
不 我妻子要生...
Oh, right. Congratulations.
哦 好吧 恭喜你了
Thank you. Thank you, sir.
谢谢 谢谢你 先生
I'm sorry, I... I really... Goodbye.
对不起 我...我真的...再见
His eyes are open.
他的眼睛睁得老大了
Don't worry about it.
别担心
Sometimes they are.
有时候 是会这样
But he isn't cowering.
可是他一点都不害怕
He's looking right at us.
他正盯着我们看
Don't worry. He'll learn to cower.
别担心 他会学会害怕的
They all do in time.
到一定时候 他们都会学会的
But he isn't!
可他没有!
Wow! He's so puny! And look at those ears!
哇喔! 他真好玩儿! 瞧那对耳朵!
And, from the very beginning,
打从一开始
Despereaux Tilling heard more,
Despereaux Tilling就比他的同类
saw more and even smelled more than any of the other mice.
听得更多 看得更多 闻得更多
Despereaux, don't do it.
Despereaux 别这么做
Don't look. Don't look!
别看 别看!
I won't, I won't.
我不看 我不看
Despereaux Tilling had no idea he was small.
Despereaux Tilling并不觉得自己很小
He wasn't just small in human terms.
其实他的个子 不仅比起人类很小
He was small even for a mouse.
连比起老鼠都算小
But, to tell you the truth, he didn't even notice.
但实话告诉你吧 他自己一点没感觉
In fact, in his own mind, Despereaux was a giant.
事实上 在他看来 Despereaux是个巨人
We're worried about him.
我们很担心他
He doesn't scurry. He doesn't cower.
他不逃跑 也不害怕
At first, we thought he would grow out of it, but...
起先 我们以为他能慢慢学会 可是...
Well, he scurries sometimes.
他有时跑得挺快
But not when he's scared!
但那不是出于害怕!
He just does it for fun.
他只是在闹着玩
And he never cowers.
他从不害怕
We've showed him how, but he...
我们试图教他 可他...
Well, some kids are slower than others.
有些孩子是学得比较慢
He'll cower in time. We'll work on it.
他会学会害怕 我们会帮他
- Yes, but... - It'll be fine, I promise.
- 好吧 不过... - 会好起来的 我保证
All right, settle down.
好了 大家安静
Ready, class?
准备好了么?
Good.
很好
Mmm! Ah!
嗯嗯
Good. Excellent.
很好 非常好
- Despereaux! - Yes?
- Despereaux! - 什么事?
You didn't cower.
你没害怕
Looks like a sword.
看起来像一把宝剑
It's a carving knife.
这是一把餐刀
It's beautiful!
它太美了!
It's dangerous.
它很危险
Do you have anymore?
你还有吗?
Despereaux, what are you doing?
Despereaux 你在干嘛?
We're not even supposed to be here.
我们不该到这儿来
That's the dungeon.
那是地牢
They have rats down there.
下面都是耗子
And they'll eat you.
他们会吃掉你的
And pull your arms off!
还会把你的胳臂撕下来!
How far down is it?
下面有多深?
I don't know. No one's ever come back.
我不知道 没人从那儿回来过
How come?
怎么会?
'Cause... 'Cause...
因为...因为...
'Cause that's where you go when you get...
因为来这里人的都是...
When you get...
都是...
Banished.
被驱逐的
What do you get banished for?
他们为什么会被驱逐?
Oh, you know.
哦 你知道的
- Rules and... - Breaking.
- 法律... - 破坏了法律
- We can't even... - Talk about it...
- 我们甚至不能... - 谈起...
- Because... - That's one of the...
- 因为... - 这也是...
Rules!
法律!
Despereaux!
I just want to have a quick look.
我只想稍微看两眼
We got to get out of here!
我们得离开这里!
Oh, gosh. - Oh, no.
- 哦 老天 - 哦 不
Oh, jeez.
哦 上帝
Despereaux! You can't feed them.
Despereaux! 你不能喂他们
Hello?
你好?
Here you go, whoever you are.
去吧 无论那是哪里
Nice.
太好了
耗子的世界
You are crazy!
你疯了
What I say? I said nothing!
我说什么了? 我什么都没说!
Well, you heard exactly what I said.
那你听清楚我说的了
- I say you crazy. - No, no, no, no!
- 我看你是疯了 - 不 不 不 不
Hurry!
快!
Ha! They look hungry, sir.
哈! 他们看起来饿坏了 先生
Dinnertime.
晚餐时间
You're not eating.
你没在吃嘛
Uh, I was.
呃...我吃过了
No, you weren't.
不 你没有
Well, I'm just watching, sir.
我只是来看看 先生
Well, that's not very grateful of you
你好像不太懂得感恩啊
after I've taken you under my wing.
在我把你纳入我羽翼下之后
Well, I'm grateful, really. I am.
我很感激 真的
You miss something, don't you?
你还在怀念什么 是不是?
Uh, no, I don't.
呃 不 我没有
There's nothing up there, Roscuro.
那上面什么都没有 Roscuro
Nothing at all.
什么都没有
Oh, no, I know that! Absolutely.
哦 我明白! 完全明白
Uh, nothing!
呃 呃 什么都没有
Nothing. Nothing at all.
没有 什么都没有
He's a tough one.
他可真顽固
You're not gonna turn him. Nah, you're not.
你改变不了他 改变不了
Oh, I don't know. A rat is a rat.
哦 我不知道 但是耗子就是耗子
It doesn't really matter where you come from.
从那儿来并不重要
I'm sorry.
我很抱歉
He is so weird.
他可真怪
No kidding.
可不是么
That is so beautiful.
真美啊
I wonder what's out there.
真想看看外面什么样
Doesn't scurry.
二月一号 不逃跑
Didn't cower.
二月三号 不害怕
"Didn't cower. Didn't cower.
不害怕 不害怕...
"Wouldn't scurry."
不逃跑
Oh, here's one: "Drew pictures of cats on his notebook."
还有一条 他在笔记本上画了只猫
- No! Cats? - Oh! I can't imagine!
- 不! 猫? - 哦! 不可想象!
I'm afraid so. Named it Fluffy.
但事实如此 还给它取名"毛毛"
- Oh, I had no idea! - Oh! That's terrible.
- 噢 我真不知道这事 - 这太可怕了
- Despereaux. - Yes, sir?
- Despereaux - 是的 先生?
Come in, please.
进来吧
Despereaux, why do you think you're in school?
Despereaux 你觉得你为什么来上学?
To learn?
来学习?
- To learn, yes. - Yes.
- 学习 是的 - 是的
To learn what?
学什么?
To learn how to be a mouse, sir.
学怎么做一只老鼠 先生
That is correct.
说的对
And you can't be a mouse if you don't learn to be afraid.
但如果你不懂害怕 就做不了老鼠
Oh, Despereaux, this...
哦 Despereaux...
There's so many wonderful things in life to be afraid of
生活中有很多美好的事物 值得你去害怕
if you'd just learn how scary they are.
只要你用心去了解它们有多可怕
Yes. Yes, sir.
是的 是的 先生
How about his brother?
他哥哥情况如何?
His brother? What about him?
他哥哥? 什么情况?
Yes, is he, you know, timid?
是的 我意思是他...胆小吗?
Oh! Oh, yes!
哦! 哦 是的!
- Yes, very timid. - Yes. So timid!
- 是的 非常胆小 - 是 特别胆小
As timid as the day is long.
整天都提心吊胆的
Good. Good.
好 好
Sometimes they just need to see the older ones do it.
有时候榜样的作用很重要
No one starts out afraid.
没有老鼠生来就害怕的
- Understood. - Of course.
- 了解了 - 当然
- You coddle that boy, that's the problem. - No.
- 都是你惯的 - 才不是
- Yes, you do. - No, no.
- 是 都是因为你 - 不 没有
- Yes, you do. You've been doing it for years. - He was always...
- 就是你 老这么惯着他 - 他总是...
He's little. I've had to help him.
他还小 我当然得帮他
He's not going to be afraid unless you allow him to be afraid.
你给要是不他机会 他是不会害怕的
Well, Furlough will teach him.
Furlough会教他的
Do what he does.
哥哥做什么你就跟着做
And don't do anything he doesn't.
他没做的千万不要做
And if he's afraid of something...
他要是害怕什么
Then you need to be afraid of it, too.
你也得学着害怕
Come on, Furlough, hurry up!
快 Furlough 快点!
All right, now, you start nibbling right along that edge there.
好了 你从那边上开始慢慢啃
The glue is all right, but it's the pages that taste the best.
胶水就不错 但纸的味道是最好的
Hmm. "Once upon a time." That's great, isn't it?
"很久很久以前" 说的真棒 是不?
"Upon a time."
"很久以前"
And they don't even tell you what time that is yet.
他们都不告诉你到底有多久
It's like you have to find that out.
好像你必须自己去发现
You're not supposed to read it, Despereaux. You're supposed to eat it.
不是让你来读书的 是让你来吃的
Good. I'll come back in an hour.
好了 我一个小时后回来
And no reading! It's a rule.
别读书! 要守规矩
Once upon a time, there lived a fair princess,
"很久很久以前 有一位美丽的公主...
fairer than any in any other land.
她比任何地方的公主都要美丽"
Hmm. Fair.
美丽
And, as the story goes, she was locked up in a faraway castle,
"后来 她被囚禁在了一座遥远的城堡里
where she could see the world but could never touch it.
在那里她可以看到这个世界 却无法触及
She longed for a prince.
她渴望能有位王子...
A brave knight who would deliver her from all of this.
一位勇敢的骑士 来把她从这一切中拯救出去
Someone with courage and honor and decency.
一个勇敢 尊贵 正派的人
But in a cruel and frightened world,
但在这个残酷 危险的世界里
men like this were scarce indeed.
这样的人实在太少了
They lived in a special world
他们生活在一个特别的世界
built on courage and chivalry and honor.
那里崇尚勇气 骑士精神 和荣耀
They pledged their lives to each other.
他们以生命互相盟誓:
To fight for truth, to defend the weak,
捍卫真理 扶助弱小...
to seek justice, and to always...
追寻正义 并永远..."
How was the library?
图书馆怎么样?
Fine.
很好
Spoil your appetite?
把你的胃口养刁了?
No. Helped it, actually.
不 事实上 让胃口变好了
Made me hungrier.
让我更饿了
Good lad.
好孩子
Ha-hah!
阿哈
Did you see they're putting up a new front on the crumb shop?
看到没? 面包屑店换了个新门面
Oh! But I loved the old front. - Quite modern. Yes.
哦! 可我还是喜欢原来的
Did a book ever speak to you?
有没有一本书 曾经跟你说过话?
Almost like it was written for you?
几乎就像是专门为你而写
Despereaux loved it all.
Despereaux爱上了这一切
Every bit of it.
书中的一切
The truth, the justice, the bravery,
真理 正义 勇气...
the sword-fighting.
剑斗
He even loved things you wouldn't suspect.
他甚至爱上了你料想不到的东西
The story said she was a prisoner,
故事中她是一名囚徒
but that wasn't totally true
但那并非完全属实
because she had hope, and whenever you have hope,
因为她还抱着希望 而只要心怀希望
you're never really anybody's prisoner.
任何人都不可能正真囚禁你
Someday, my prince will come.
有一天 我的王子会出现
But how did she know that?
但她又怎么知道呢?
Yeah, how did she know that?
是啊 她怎么知道?
Why are you crying?
你为什么哭?
Down here.
我在这下面
Are you a rat?
你是只耗子?
No.
不
What are you? A mouse?
那你是什么? 老鼠?
I am a gentleman.
我是位绅士
And how do you do?
你好啊
You're sad.
你很难过
Yes.
是的
Because you have longing.
因为你有渴望
You're a strange little mouse.
你是只奇怪的小老鼠
Thank you.
谢谢
Come on.
过来
Where did you hear that?
你从哪听来的?
About the longing.
关于渴望
In a story.
从一个故事里
A story? About what?
故事? 讲什么的?
About a princess, like you, in a castle, like this.
讲一个公主 就像你 在一座城堡里 就像这里
Oh. You're a smooth little mouse, aren't you?
哦 你真是个能说会道的小老鼠
Bet you tell that to all the princesses.
我打赌你对所有的公主都这么说
I am sworn to tell the truth.
我发誓只讲真话
It is a code of honor.
这是种诚信准则
Ah. Not just a gentleman, an honorable gentleman.
噢 你不仅是位绅士 还是位可敬的绅士
Well, then, how does this story end
那么 故事结局是什么呢?
with this princess who's locked in a castle?
那个被囚禁在城堡的公主
I don't know...
我不知道...
I haven't finished it yet.
我还没有读完
I'd love to know.
我想知道
Oh, I wish it would rain.
哦 我希望能下场雨
I wish there was soup again.
我希望能再喝到汤
I even wish there were rats!
我甚至希望还有耗子!
Will you promise me that?
你可以答应我吗?
Will you promise to finish your story and tell me how it ends?
答应我看完故事 告诉我结局?
Yes. It will be my quest.
好的 这将是我的追求
Your quest! You are a very brave mouse.
你的追求! 你真是只勇敢的小老鼠
Thank you, my good gentleman.
谢谢你 我的好绅士
Now, there are all kinds of princesses.
世界上有各种各样的公主
Some are born that way,
一些出生就是公主
some marry into it,
一些是嫁给了王子
and some are destined to be princesses
而还有一些 却只有在自己的想象中
only in their own minds.
才能成为公主
But at one time or another,
但总有那么些时候
every little girl longs to be a princess.
每个小女孩都希望成为公主
I'm gonna live right there.
我以后就要住在那儿
Right up there, near the tippy-top.
就在那 就在那尖顶上
Quit your daydreaming and feed those swine!
少做白日梦了 快喂猪!
Yes, I know. It's gonna be all mine.
我知道 总有一天那会是我的
No, you deaf little urchin. I said feed those swine!
你这丫头聋啦 我说了 快 喂 猪!
Miggery Sow had been shoveling slop
在Miggery Sow的记忆中
for as long as she could remember.
她已经铲猪食好多年了
Her Uncle Ned had put a shovel in her hand from the minute she could hold one.
她刚拿得动铲子 他叔叔Ned就逼她干活
But it turned out all right
但是结果还不错
because she got on quite nicely with the pigs.
因为她和小猪处的很好
That's right.
没错
I'm gonna have a special room just for my dresses
我会有一整间房间专门放衣服
and another whole closet just for my knickers!
还有一个大衣橱 专门放我的短裤!
In fact, Miggery Sow could see her future so clearly.
事实上 Miggery Sow 可以清晰的看到她的未来
She could see the tiara, the fancy dresses, the maids-in-waiting,
她可以看到皇冠 漂亮裙子 还有仕女
and when things got really bad around the farm,
而当农场生活难以忍受的时候
she could see the moment that she would finally be delivered from all of this.
她还能看到 她从这一切中解脱的时刻
Not long now.
不会太久的
I promise you that.
我发誓
20 for the big ones, 15 for the sow, and 12 for the girl.
大的20 母猪15 女孩12
15 for the girl, same as the sow.
女孩15 和母猪一个价
I told you! I told you I'd make it to the castle!
我说过的 我说过的! 我要去城堡了!
Whoa!
哦噢
So sometimes, it doesn't take much for your dreams to come true.
所以有时候 梦想成真并不难
You just have to be able to see it that way.
只要你能够这么认为
She was beautiful! Like an angel.
她真漂亮 就像一个天使
You are crazy.
你疯了
And she smelled so amazing.
她的气味真好闻
Like a garden.
像花园
Despereaux!
You can't talk to a human.
你不能和人类说话
That is the worst thing you can do.
这是你最不该做的事
No, it's the best thing I ever did.
不 这是我做过的最棒的事
They will throw you in the dungeon.
他们会把你关进地牢
You will get eaten by rats!
你会被耗子吃了
It would be worth it.
就算这样也值得
They could tear at my flesh.
他们可以把我撕裂
Oh, this is bad.
哦 太糟了
Oh, and when she held me in her hand, it was...
哦 当她把我托在手里...
It was so soft, like floating in a pillow.
是那么柔软 就好像漂在云端
You know what? I'm worried about you.
你知道吗? 我很担心你
That's the point, Furlough.
这就是重点 Furlough
There's nothing to be afraid of.
根本没什么好怕的
Quiet! They will hear you.
轻点! 他们会听到的
Come on. Just try it.
来吧 你应该试试
Just for a second, just try being brave.
就这么一会儿 试着变勇敢些
- Oh! - And stop cowering!
- 哦! - 别再害怕了!
What's going on in here?
这是怎么回事?
What's all this talk about princesses and bravery?
你们为什么在说什么公主 ...什么勇敢?
Furlough, I want to see you in my study, right now.
Furlough 你到我的书房来 马上
Are you sure? - That's what he said.
- 你确定? - 他就是这么说的
- A real human? - A princess.
- 一个人类? - 一个公主
We need to tell them.
我们得告诉他们
We need to tell the Mouse Council.
我们得告诉老鼠议会
- But they'll... - This is bad. This is very bad.
- 但是他们会... - 太糟了 真是太糟糕了
If they find out... If they find out that they didn't find out...
如果他们发现 如果他们发现了 他们没有发现的...
Oh, then they'll find out that it was me who...
哦 他们会发现的 是我...
Oh, no.
哦 不
But they will send him to the dungeon!
可他们会把他关进地牢的!
- Oh, he'll get eaten by rats! - Oh!
- 哦 他会被耗子吃了! - 哦!
No, not if we beg.
不 如果我们恳求的话就不会
If we really beg and show them that he's changed.
如果我们真心地恳求 告诉他们他在改变
That he's afraid.
他会害怕
That he's afraid, and he's turned into a real mouse.
他会害怕 然后他会变成一只正的老鼠
Despereaux!
Of course, destiny is a funny thing.
当然 命运很有意思
We go out to meet it, and we don't always know that we are.
我们出去和它相遇 但有时我们并不自知
For glory and honor!
为荣耀和自豪!
Surround him!
包围他!
Despereaux Tilling.
Despereaux Tilling
How long have you been working on this book?
你读这本书多久了?
Hmm... A week?
恩...一个礼拜?
A week? You've hardly cracked it.
一周? 你毫无悔意嘛
Well, I was...
恩 我只是...
I just wanted to see how it ends.
我只是想知道结局
Refused training as a mouse.
拒绝接受老鼠的教育
Refused to respect the will and guidance of elder mice.
无视长者的意愿和教诲
Repeatedly engaged in bold and un-meek behavior.
一再做出胆大妄为的行为
Triggered willfully not less than 17 mousetraps.
蓄意触发至少17个老鼠夹
Just shameful!
真是可耻!
Had personal contact with...
私自接触...
With...
接触...
With a human being.
接触人类
Isn't there something you can do?
你不能做点什么吗?
Antoinette, stop right now! Stop that.
Antoinette 别说了! 别说了
You have to trust them.
你必须信任他们
They are the Council.
他们是议会
They're the Council because...
他们是议会是因为...
Because they're the Council.
因为...他们...是议会
They're the Council.
他们是议会
Is there anything you wish to say in your defense?
你还有什么想为自己辩护的吗?
Well, it was a very good story,
恩 那是个很棒的故事
and she was a very beautiful princess.
她是一个很美的公主
Despereaux Tilling,
Despereaux Tilling
our laws are here to protect us and our way of life.
我们的法律旨在保护我们 以及我们的生活方式
And when one of our citizens strays from that way of life,
当我们中有人偏离了这种生活方式
he becomes a threat to us all.
他就会成为我们大家的威胁
It's an easy question.
问题很简单
Are you a man or are you a mouse?
你是人 还是老鼠?
And your actions have told us
你的行为已经告诉了我们
that you have a great deal of trouble being a mouse.
要你做只老鼠很困难
It is the judgment of this court
议会现在判决
that you should be banished from these walls forever.
你将被永远流放
You shall be remanded into the custody of Hovis, the Threadmaster,
线绳大师Hovis会押送你
who will prepare you for your descent into the dungeons of Dor,
把你送去多尔国的地牢
from which no mouse and no light has ever escaped.
在那里 从没有一只老鼠逃脱 从没有一丝光明泄漏
- Shh! - My baby!
- 嘘! - 我的孩子!
Quiet. Be quiet, my dear. There's nothing to be done.
安静 亲爱的 这也是没办法的事
Come with me.
跟我走
Stand there.
站在那
Red?
红色?
Ah, so they tell me.
啊 他们是这么告诉我的
So you're the brave one.
你是只勇敢的老鼠
I guess.
也许吧
It's good. It'll carry well down there.
好了 会安全把你放下去
Wear it proudly.
为你的勇敢骄傲吧
There's no shame.
没什么好羞耻的
It's time.
到时间了
It's all right. They're too scared to come down here.
没什么的 他们都太胆小不敢下去
In there?
这里?
I'm afraid so.
我恐怕是的
Courage, right?
勇气 对吗?
And truth.
还有真理
- And honor. - Good.
- 还有荣誉 - 很好
But especially courage.
但特别要有勇气
I'm ready.
我准备好了
All right, then you need to...
好吧 然后你要...
What? Whoa!
什么? 哇!
Hello? Hello?
哈喽? 哈喽?
Whoa!
哇哦
Lads, let's go, on the double!
小的们 撤 赶紧地!
Who is that?
谁?
Who goes there?
谁在那儿?
Who is that?
谁啊?
Despereaux Tilling.
Despereaux Tilling
Are you a man or are you a mouse?
你是人 还是老鼠?
I am a gentleman.
我是绅士
Oh.
哦
- It's a mouse. - I'm hungry.
- 是只老鼠 - 我饿了
Shh! Quiet, lads. Patience.
嘘! 安静 小的们 耐心点
And what makes you a gentleman?
是什么让你成了绅士的?
A code...
诚信...
A code of honor.
诚信准则
You're a strange little mouse, aren't you?
你真是只奇怪的小老鼠 对吧?
And where did you find this code of honor?
你从哪儿听来的"诚信准则"?
Well, in a legend.
在一个传说里
A legend that I read.
我读过的一个传说
Fine. Oh, tell me this legend of yours.
好吧 跟说说你那个传说
I could do with a good story right now.
现在听段精彩的故事也不错
Well,
嗯
it's about a princess and a knight
故事讲的是一位公主 和一个骑士
and his quest to save her honor.
还有他捍卫她的荣誉的历程
Ah. It was a princess that took away my soup.
啊 让我喝不了汤的就是个公主
She didn't take it.
不是她干的
In fact, she misses it, too!
实际上 她也想念汤!
How do you know all this, then?
你怎么知道得这么清楚?
I've seen her.
我见过她
- Seen her? - I've talked to her.
- 见过她? - 和她说过话
- Talked to her? - That's why they sent me down here.
- 还说过话? - 所以我被驱逐到这儿来
Mmm-hmm. And what did this princess tell you
嗯 那跟你这个小听众...
when you had your little audience?
公主都说了些啥?
Eh? Eh?
呵?
Oh, you must be a royal mouse. Is that it?
你肯定是只皇室老鼠 是不是?
She told me that she missed the soup and the rain
她说她想念汤 还有雨
and, most of all, the sunlight.
最想念的是阳光
And that she just wanted it all to come back again.
她希望这一切都能重新回来
Well, I don't want to hear your little stories
我不想听你的故事了
about princesses and sunshine.
什么公主啊阳光的
Go tell them to the rats!
还是和耗子们说去吧!
All right, boys, come on!
好 孩儿们 上啊!
Good crowd, isn't it, sir?
观众很多 是吧 先生?
Yes, it is, quite.
没错 的确很多
Mouse! Mouse! Mouse! Mouse!
老鼠! 老鼠! 老鼠! 老鼠!
Ah, Roscuro! I'm glad you could make it.
哦 Roscuro! 很高兴你也来了
I thought you didn't like the arena.
我还以为你不喜欢竞技场呢
Huh? Oh! No, no. It... It's an honor, sir.
哦 不 不 很荣幸能来这里 先生
Oh!
哦
- Good. - Mmm.
- 很好 - 嗯
Well, enjoy.
来吧 尽情享受
Oh, uh... Thank you.
哦 呃...谢谢
Let the games begin!
游戏开始!
Mouse! Mouse! Mouse!
老鼠! 老鼠! 老鼠!
Come on!
上啊
Hold on!
抓紧了!
Eat! Eat! Eat!
吃了他! 吃了他! 吃了他!
Wait!
等等!
Can I have him? Can I have this one? Please?
能把他给我吗? 求你了
What?
什么?
It's just that that one looks tasty.
就是 他看起来...很好吃的样子
Well, this is progress.
有进步了嘛
Perhaps we're starting to leave the past behind us, eh?
也许我们应该尽释前嫌 呃?
Enjoy, my friend.
好好享用 我的朋友
Don't leave a morsel.
一口都不要剩
Oh, I won't.
哦 我不会的
Pull!
拉回来!
Come on, let's go, buster!
动作快点 我们走 小鬼!
That's it. That's it. You keep moving!
就这样 就这样 快给我走!
It's okay. Keep walking.
没事的 继续往前走
Come on, keep moving! Let's go, come on!
快点 往前走! 快!
It's right up there.
就在那上面
- Huh? - Keep walking.
继续往前走
- Oh. - See that?
- 哦 - 看见没?
Light. Real light.
光 真正的光
It's mine, but you can share it.
这是我的 不过你也可以分享
It isn't much, but there isn't much anywhere since everything turned gray.
不是很多 但世界变得灰暗后 哪儿都没有很多的光了
You're not gonna eat me?
你不吃我?
No. I don't eat mice.
不 我不吃老鼠
Then what do you eat?
那你吃啥?
Crumbs.
面包屑
When I can find them.
如果能找到的话
So you are a gentleman.
这么说 你是绅士
Tell me that story.
跟我说说那个故事
About the Princess.
公主的故事
Tell me what she looked like.
说说她什么样儿
Well, she was...
呃 她...
Was she angry?
她有没有生气?
No.
没有
No, not at all.
一点都没有
Her heart was full of longing.
她内心充满了...渴望
What's longing?
什么是渴望?
And that's how a friendship is born.
一段友谊就这样诞生了
Over the next few weeks, he told Roscuro everything he knew about loyalty
接下来的几个星期里 他把他知道的都告诉了Roscuro
and honor and chivalry and courage.
忠诚 荣誉 侠义和勇气
He told him about the Princess, and where her longing came from.
他说了公主的事 说到她为什么会有渴望
That she missed the rain and the soup and even the rats.
说到她想念雨水 汤汁 甚至是耗子
Even the rats?
甚至是耗子?
He told him about their code of honor, about his noble quest,
他跟他说了诚信准则 说了他高尚的追求
about duty and loyalty.
说到了责任和忠诚
And there, in the darkness of the cellar,
就在这个黑暗的地牢里
two knights pledged devotion to a princess who was trapped inside a castle.
两位骑士许下郑重承诺 要解救困在堡垒中的公主
Trapped in a life full of pain and longing.
公主的生活充满痛苦和渴望
Even if no one could tell.
哪怕没有人知道
Your crown, ma'am.
您的王冠 殿下
Oh.
哦
I don't want it today.
我今天不想戴
But it's beautiful, ma'am.
但它多漂亮啊 殿下
I know, but I don't want it.
我知道 但我今天不想戴
You look so pretty in it, ma'am.
你戴上很好看的 殿下
Like a princess.
就象公主一样
I know. I am the princess.
我知道 我就是公主
Oh, I know, ma'am,
我知道的 殿下
but such a fine princess, with a little, pretty, glittery...
不过 这么漂亮的公主 戴上这个美丽闪耀的小皇冠...
I don't want it!
我不想戴!
All right, Mig?
行不行 Mig?
Very well, ma'am.
好的 殿下
Please, take it away.
请把它拿走
Princess.
公主
Who's the princess?
谁是公主?
I'm a princess.
我是公主
I'm the princess.
我才是公主
My comb, my hat, my gloves
我的梳子 我的王冠 我的手套
and my pretty powder
还有我美丽的粉扑
on my pretty princess face.
扑在我美丽的公主脸蛋上
And what do you think you're doing?
你在做什么?
Ma'am!
夫人!
Where did you get all this?
你从哪儿拿的这些东西?
I just borrowed it, ma'am.
我借来的 夫人
Borrowed it?
借来的?
I was gonna put them all back.
我会还回去的
See that you do!
看看你做的好事!
And you can spend the whole week
这个礼拜
taking slop to the dungeon
你就去地牢里送饭吧
for your little escapade.
居然做出这种事
"Princess"!
还"公主"呢!
God! She's the princess.
上帝啊! 她才是公主
And now I have to carry the sloppy, gloppy, stinky stew
而我只能端着又油又脏又臭的餐盘
down in the damp, dark, dingy...
来这个又湿又黑又破的...
A person could get lost forever down here.
在这儿还真容易迷路啊
Din-din.
叮叮
Slop.
上饭
No, don't stop! I said "slop"!
不 别傻站着! 我说让你上饭!
How am I supposed to eat this swill?
这种猪食让我怎么吃?
Oh, stop that! I don't have to be putting up with all this!
别这样! 我没必要看你脸色!
I serve the Princess.
我是伺候公主的
Right. You serve the Princess.
是啊 你是伺候公主的
- That's a bit of a laugh, isn't it? - I do.
- 真搞笑 是不是? - 是真的
- I bring her tea and... - Well, I don't want to hear it!
- 我给她端茶... - 我才不要听!
Had me own little princess once.
以前我也有个小公主的
And now I don't.
现在没了
Oh. What, you had a princess?
哦 你有个公主?
Yeah.
是啊
Every dad's got a princess.
每个做爸爸的都有个小公主
Till he stops being a dad, of course.
当然 直到他不能再做爸爸
Sorry. So, so, sorry!
对不起 真的真的对不起!
Oh, well, I've got a real one.
我可是有个真正的公主
And she's got a tiara and fancy robes,
她有王冠 漂亮的礼服
and she's got shiny bits all over every frock in her closet.
她衣橱里每件衣服都亮闪闪的
And I get to see her every single day.
而且我每天都能见到她
What kind of a quest?
你的追求是什么?
Uh...
呃...
To right a terrible wrong.
去弥补一个严重的错误
But who did you wrong?
你的错误害了谁?
Okay.
好吧
Do you remember when they banished the rats?
你还记得耗子被驱逐的事吗?
- Sure. Yes. - Okay.
- 当然记得 - 好
Well, it wasn't all the rats they banished.
不是所有的耗子都应该被驱逐
I mean, they did, but it was all because of one particular rat
那都是一只耗子惹的祸
in particular.
全是因为它
If I could just tell her I'm sorry,
如果我能向她道歉
that I'm, you know, I'm really sorry.
告诉她 我真的很抱歉
And that I didn't mean for any of this to happen.
我不想事情变成这样子
If she could just hear me say it,
如果她能听我说
you know, just... Just hear my voice,
只要听听我的声音
she would know how much I meant it.
她就会知道我是多么诚恳
That is a very noble quest.
这是个非常高尚的追求
Your Highness?
殿下?
Is that you?
是你吗?
My little mouse?
我的小老鼠?
Oh, I'm not a mouse. I...
哦 我不是老鼠 我...
I'm a...
我是...
I forgot.
我忘了
You're my little gentleman, aren't you?
你是我的小绅士 是不是?
Have you come to tell me how the story ends?
你是来告诉我故事的结局吗?
Did you finish your quest?
你的追求达成了吗?
Where are you?
你在哪儿啊?
I have come to apologize.
我是来道歉的
Oh, you are noble, remember?
哦 你是高尚的 还记得吗?
You have nothing to be sorry about.
你没有什么可道歉的
Oh, but I am.
噢 我有的
I am sorry.
我很抱歉
I know you.
我认识你
- No, no. - Oh, no!
- 别 别 - 不要过来!
No! Please, please listen. Please.
别这样! 请听我说 拜托
- A rat! - Please. I just want to tell you.
- 耗子! - 求你了 我就是想告诉你...
Someone, please!
来人啊!
Listen. It's okay.
听着 没事的
Get it off me! There's a rat in my room!
滚开! 我房间里有只耗子!
Please get him off!
请把它弄走!
What?
什么?
Rat!
耗子!
It's a rat!
是只耗子!
Quick, rush him!
快 追上他!
Get him!
抓住他!
Filthy rodent!
肮脏的耗子!
Where'd he go?
他去哪儿了
What would you do if your own name was a bad word?
如果你的名字是个脏词 你该怎么办?
If John or Beth or Bill was an insult.
如果说John或Beth或Bill是种侮辱
Well, that's how Roscuro came to feel about who he was.
Roscuro觉得自己就是这样
When your heart breaks, it can grow back crooked.
心灵破碎时 它可能会扭曲
It grows back twisted and gnarled and hard.
会变得阴暗 麻木 冷酷
Even as he changed, Roscuro still had longing.
虽然他改变了 Roscuro还有着渴望
But now he just longed for someone whose heart was as hardened as his was.
但现在 他只渴望找到 和他一样铁石心肠的人
Pretty princess. Pretty, pretty princess pie.
美丽的公主 漂亮动人的公主
What a pretty princess!
多么漂亮的公主啊!
My gloves.
我的手套
My comb.
我的梳子
My jewel-y, girly hat,
我镶着宝石的小王冠
all sitting on my princess head.
戴在我的公主头上
Who's the pretty princess pumpkin pie?
谁是美丽的公主?
You are.
你是
Right. I am.
是啊 我是
You are. And you should be dressed in those clothes.
你是 你应该穿上那些漂亮衣服
Quite right. I should.
说得没错 确实应该
Mmm-hmm. And you should lounge in that bed.
嗯 你应该躺在那张公主床上
Lounging.
闲散地躺着
Lounging round, yes, the whole day!
闲散地度过一整天!
And you should be wearing that crown.
而且你应该戴那个王冠
I should be wearing a frown?
我应该皱眉?
No. No, no, no. Not a frown. A crown.
不不 不是皱眉 是王冠
Wow! Can't hear me own self think.
哇 我听见自己在想什么了
- Ah! - Shh!
- 啊! - 嘘!
Shh!
- Ah! - Shh!
- 啊! - 嘘!
Who are you?
你是谁?
I'm here to help you.
我是来帮你的
I can't be caught with a real rat in my bunk.
不能让人发现我房间里有耗子
I don't think so.
不能这样
And what if they find you with a painting of the Princess?
如果让人发现你私藏公主画像怎么办?
You think that's as bad as a rat?
你觉得这和窝藏耗子一样糟吗?
I want the same thing you do.
我们有共同的目标
Allo?
谁呀?
What are you doing?
你干嘛呢?
Uh...
呃...
I need it for a baby.
我来为宝宝拿刀
No, not a baby!
不 不是宝宝!
For milady.
是夫人
I mean milady.
我是说夫人
Yes.
是的
To chop apples.
切苹果用的
She'd like some apples.
她想吃苹果
Now turn and leave.
现在转身离开
No, no! Just turn and leave.
不是! 是让你转身离开
Oh, right. Sorry.
是哦 不好意思
Sorry. Bye.
不好意思 拜
Oh, I can't hear you, see, because deaf, but...
我听不清你说啥 有点耳背
A bit deaf.
一点点而已
You know, hurt is a funny thing.
伤害是件很奇妙的事
The same thing that makes one person angry can put another person into grief.
它能让一个人愤怒 却让另一个人悲伤
Here, take care of me little princess.
来 照顾我的小公主吧
I can't no more.
我再也照顾不了了
Oh, I will. Don't worry.
哦 我会的 别担心
I'm sorry.
对不起
Sorry. So, so sorry!
真的 真的对不起!
Gregory always said that she had too much heart.
Gregory常说她的心眼太多了
And that's why they had to put some of it on the outside.
所以有些得放在看得见的地方
But let's face it.
但事实是
It's hard to see something on your back.
我们很难看见背后长了什么
In fact, you can have a good heart and not even know it.
实际上 你可能有颗善良的心 自己却不知道
You can do this. You know you can.
你做得到的 你知道你行的
I know I can.
我知道我行
She belongs in the dungeon, and you belong in the palace, like a princess.
她应该去地牢 而你应该在宫殿里 就像个公主
What are you doing?
你在干什么?
I'm cleaning, ma'am.
打扫卫生 殿下
With rope?
用绳子打扫?
It helps, ma'am.
用得上的 殿下
Well, stop it. You look ridiculous.
别说了 你看上去真可笑
Sorry, ma'am?
你说什么 殿下?
I said you look ridiculous.
我说 你看上去真可笑
Ridiculous, ridiculous, ridiculous.
可笑 可笑 可笑
- You can't do this, Mig. - Gor.
- 你不能这么做 Mig - 走
Seems I am, ma'am.
我现在不就这么做了么 殿下
You'll get in a terrible amount of trouble.
你会惹上大麻烦的
Don't listen. You're the princess now.
别听她说 现在你是公主
I'm the princess now.
现在我是公主
And you belong in the palace.
你应该住进宫殿
I belong in the palace.
我应该住进宫殿
And she belongs in...
她应该...
No! You can't do this!
不 你不能这么做!
Help! Help! Someone help me!
救命啊! 救命! 谁来救救我!
Help! Help!
救命! 救命! 救救我啊!
救命! 救命!
Help! Help!
Help!
救命!
I'm in here!
我在这儿!
Help!
救命!
You filthy, stinking rat!
你这个肮脏的死耗子!
You tricked me!
你骗了我!
Here's the spot, rats!
就是这儿了 耗子们!
What's Roscuro brought us, then?
Roscuro给我们带什么来了?
Hungry! Yum! Hungry now!
好饿! 好饿啊!
Not yet, lads. No, no, you've got to wait.
现在不行 伙计们 不 再等等
It's nowhere near dinnertime.
离晚饭时间还远着呢
Oh, come on, Smudge, I'm starving.
哦拜托 Smudge 我要饿死了
Something special for dinner tonight.
今晚有美味哦
Smells delicious!
好香!
Smells human to me. A young one. - And not just any human.
- 像是人味儿 年轻人 - 不是一般的人
Let's have a look. - It's the Princess!
- 来看看 - 是个公主!
Oi, you'll wait for your dinner like everyone else.
喂 你得跟别人一样 等到晚饭时间
Come on, Smudge, give us a little look.
拜托 Smudge 让我们看一眼嘛
No, no, no!
不行 不行 不行!
Boss doesn't want her getting nervous. Spoils the meat, doesn't it?
老大不想让她紧张 要善待美食 不是吗?
Milady!
殿下!
Psst! Milady!
噗嘶! 殿下!
Oh, my little mouse! It's you.
哦 我的小老鼠! 是你
I will deliver you from this evil, ma'am.
我会救你出来的 殿下
Oh, no. Just go find my father.
哦不 你去找我的父亲
Take this chain from around my neck.
拿着我脖子上这条项链
To show him you are honest and truthful.
向他证明你的诚实 可靠
Oh, I am! Honest and truthful and loyal and...
我本来就是啊! 诚实 可靠 忠诚...
I know.
我知道
But hurry.
不过要快
Here. Take it.
来 拿着
There isn't much time.
没有多少时间了
Hey, did you get some? - Oh, yeah.
- 嘿 拿了吗? - 当然
Here you are, sir.
这个给您 先生
Fresh worms.
新鲜的蠕虫
Thank you.
谢谢
Well done, Roscuro!
干的漂亮 Roscuro!
You hear that?
听到了吗?
That's all because of you.
这都是你的功绩
Come, my friend. Look at your handiwork.
来 我的朋友 看看你的杰作
King! King! Sire, your daughter is in danger!
国王! 国王! 陛下 您的女儿现在很危险!
Sire, up here!
国王 往上看!
Your Highness! Please, sir!
殿下! 求你了 先生!
Oh, come on.
哦 拜托
Hey, Sire!
嘿 陛下!
Your Highness!
殿下!
Look, Your Highness! Look!
看看啊 殿下 看看我!
Hello, Mr. King!
你好 国王殿下!
Hey, hello!
嘿 你好!
Down here! Hello! Down here!
看下面! 喂! 看下面!
Listen, your daughter is in danger!
听着 你女儿现在很危险!
She's in a dungeon!
她在地牢里!
You're the only one who can help!
只有你能救她!
She sent me to get you!
是她让我来找你的!
Sir, please! Sir...
先生 求你了! 先生...
Ooh! Sire!
陛下!
Your Highness!
殿下!
Look down here! Whoa!
往 下 看!
Dad? Dad, listen. You've got to help me.
爸? 爸 听我说 你得帮帮我
But you're dead!
可 可你不是死了吗!
No. No, I'm not. I'm not dead!
不 不 我没死!
Now, listen. The Princess is in danger. She's locked in the dungeon.
听着 公主现在身陷险境 她被关在地牢里呢
Oh, my golly, you're dead.
哦 天呐 你已经死 死 死了
Dad! Dad, I'm not dead!
爸! 爸 我没死
Dad, I'm not dead! Oh, Dad, wake up, please!
爸 我没死! 哦爸爸 快醒醒啊 求你了!
Furlough, listen. You've gotta help me.
Furlough 听着 你得帮帮我
You're...
你 你 你...
No. No, I'm not dead.
不 不 我没死
Listen, the Princess is in danger. She's locked in the cellar.
听着 公主现在身陷险境 她被关在牢里呢
Oh, my God, you're dead!
哦我的上帝 你已经死了啊!
No!
没有!
Guys? Listen.
伙计们? 听着
Okay, look. Now, I'm not dead.
好 现在听着 我没有死
The Princess is in danger, and she's down in the dungeon
公主现在身陷险境 她被关在地牢里
and you've gotta... You've gotta help me!
你们要...你们要帮帮我啊!
Somebody?
有人能帮帮我吗?
Whoa!
哇哦!
Hmm.
嗯
Oh!
哦
Oh, I must have been...
哦 我一定是在...
Enough!
我受够了!
Voil?
Look at you! You are still brewing tea.
看看你! 你这是在煮茶呢
If you want to make a statement, what do I say?
你要是想做汤 我怎么跟你说的?
Make it a good one!
做得好点儿!
Ah, it's so great to see you!
啊 能见到你真是太好了!
Fantastic!
太棒了!
- Ah. - Marjoram?
- 嗯 - 媒墨角兰(一种植物)?
Mmm-hmm. Love it. Perfect.
恩 我喜欢 完美
- Ah! Superbe! - Bellissima!
- 啊! 完美! - 无与伦比!
Basil, will you look at that?
Basil 你看啊
Oh!
哦
Look up there! Marge, come and have a look at this!
快看上面! Marge 快来看看!
Oh, my!
哦 我的天呐!
Mmm!
嗯
Cauliflower?
是花椰菜吗?
Perfect. Perfect, yes, it's about time.
完美 完美 关键看火候
Basilico.
罗勒(水果)
Eh, some celery?
恩 加点芹菜吗?
Hey, hello!
嘿 你好!
Good, celery. Parsley, maybe.
好 芹菜 欧芹吧
The Princess is in danger! - No, no, no.
- 公主正身陷险境! - 不 不 不
- Garlic! Should I use the garlic? - Look down here!
- 蒜! 要不要加蒜啊? - 往下看啊!
- I mean not too much, but just a little bit. - Oh, no, no, no, of course.
- 别加太多 一点就够 - 哦 不会不会 当然
- It is fantastic! - Yes.
- 简直太棒了! - 是啊
Bellissima!
太诱人了!
Brav-ow!
太诱...啊!
Oh.
哦
The Princess is in danger!
公主正身陷险境!
Ooh!
嗯
You are a cute little mouse.
你是只可爱的小老鼠
Would you like some soup?
想不想喝点汤?
No, I don't want...
不 我不想...
The Princess is in danger!
公主正身陷险境!
And a talking mouse, too.
还是只会说话的老鼠
Listen, you've gotta help me.
听着 你得帮帮我
Perhaps a little cheese?
想要点儿奶酪吗?
No, I don't want any cheese!
不 我不要奶酪!
The Princess! She's in danger!
公主! 她现在很危险!
She's locked in the dungeon!
她被关在地牢里呢!
In the dungeon!
在地牢里!
Oh, don't be silly, my little mouse.
哦 别傻了 我的小老鼠
Everything is fine!
一切都好着呢!
The Princess is perfectly safe up in her...
公主好好地待在她的...
Oh, my.
哦 上帝
Boldo!
Look! It's...
快看! 是...
Boldo.
Boldo?
Where are you?
你在哪儿呢?
Charge!
冲啊!
Tell me again.
再说一遍
- Chivalry! - Mmm.
骑士精神!
- Bravery! - Mmm-hmm.
勇敢!
Honor!
还有光荣!
Chivalry! Bravery! Honor!
骑士精神! 勇敢! 光荣!
I love it!
我喜欢!
Oh, it feels so good to be out of the kitchen!
哦 走出厨房的感觉太好了!
Let's go!
我们走!
Into the breach!
攻进缺口!
Down there.
往下
Andiamo!
前进!
Whoa!
哇哦
Ha-ha!
哈哈
Where did she go?
她去哪儿了?
My friends!
我的朋友!
My friends, there are rats,
我的朋友 这儿有耗子
and then there are rats!
然后 还是耗子!
And I would like a huge round of applause
让我们以热烈掌声
for our good friend here
欢迎我们的朋友
for delivering us our princess!
给我们带来了公主!
Come on, let's go!
来吧 快走!
Oi! Hang on! Where you going? Help!
喂! 等等! 你要去哪儿? 救我啊!
Hurry!
快点儿!
Look at that!
看那儿!
Let's get him, boys.
赶紧抓住他 小的们
Keep going! Keep going!
快跑 别停!
Please! Oh, no, get off of me!
拜托! 哦 不 别碰我!
Nice shot!
打得漂亮!
That's my onion!
那是我的洋葱!
Hello?
你好?
Help!
救命!
Can anybody hear me?
有人吗?
Help!
救命!
I'm in here!
我在这儿呢!
Oh, gor!
哦 Gor!
What took you so long?
你怎么才来?
I've been screaming in here for over two hours.
我在这儿都喊了两个多小时了
My little princess.
我的小公主
Rain.
下雨了
Yes.
是啊
Papa! Papa, look!
爸爸! 爸爸 看呐!
Up there!
上面!
The sun!
是太阳!
Go on, Despereaux.
快去吧 Despereaux
Wait! Wait just a moment! Patience!
等等! 等一等! 耐心点儿!
Not just yet.
即 将 开 始
The honor is all yours, my friend.
荣耀属于你 我的朋友
Eat! Eat! Eat!
吃! 吃! 吃!
Okay, remember when we said that grief
好了 记不记得我们说过悲伤...
was the strongest thing a person could feel?
是人类最强烈的情感?
Well, it isn't.
其实 它不是的
It's forgiveness.
宽恕才是
Because a single act of forgiveness can change everything.
因为宽恕能改变一切
No.
不
What?
什么?
No.
不
You worthless little...
你个没用的...
Eat! Eat! Eat!
吃! 吃! 吃!
Help!
救命!
Who let him out?
谁放他出来的?
Hey, you!
嘿 你!
It's that mouse!
是那只老鼠!
Get him!
抓住他!
Ah, if it isn't our brave little knight.
啊 多亏了我们勇敢的小骑士
- I wonder. - No!
- 我在想 - 不要!
Should I finish you off myself
我是该亲手结果了你呢
or turn you into cat food?
还是该让你做猫食?
Here, kitty, kitty, kitty.
这儿 猫咪 猫咪 猫咪
What is that?
那 是 什么?
Please. Nice kitty?
拜托 好猫咪?
No, no, no, no!
不 不 不 不!
Hmm?
呃?
Thank you, my good gentleman.
谢谢 我的好绅士
I am sorry.
我很抱歉
I'm the one who should be sorry.
该道歉的是我
I'm so, so sorry. You've no idea how sorry I am.
我真的 真的很抱歉 你想像不到我有多愧疚
That's all right.
没关系
I'm so sorry.
我很抱歉
So, you could call all of this
如果你愿意的话
a big misunderstanding if you wanted to.
可以当这一切是个大大的误会
A king was hurt, so he hurt a rat.
一个国王受伤了 便伤害了耗子
And a rat was hurt, so he hurt a princess.
耗子受伤了 便伤害了公主
And a princess was hurt, so she hurt a servant girl,
公主受伤了 便于无意间
without even meaning to do it.
伤害了一个女仆
And that servant had been hurting for so long,
而那女仆已经被伤害了太久
that almost nothing could make her feel better.
几乎没有什么事能让她感觉好些
But was it a mistake or was it just good luck?
可这一切是个错误 还是好事呢?
Because the servant girl went back to her farm.
因为女仆回到了她的农庄
And the jailer finally found his princess.
狱卒终于找到了他的公主
And the King found something stronger than grief.
国王发现了比悲伤更强烈的情感
And the mice finally got rid of their fear.
老鼠们终于摆脱了恐惧
And the people of Dor lived side by side with their rats.
多尔国的人们和耗子们和平相处
All except one.
除了一只耗子
Who went back to sea
他重返了大海
and felt a cool breeze each morning
他在清晨享受微风
and the sun in his face every afternoon.
在下午沐浴阳光
And we'd tell you that they all lived happily ever after, but...
他们从此都过上了幸福的生活 可是...
Whoa!
哇哦!
what fun is that?
很有趣吧?
Whoa!
哇哦!